*music*
I know, I knew that would get a rise out of you guys.
No, I, Ryan's talked about it multiple times.
One of our core values is uniting for the sake of the gospel.
And we were, I was actually in the car this morning, we were listening to a song.
I believe it's, don't quote me on this.
I think it was Phil Wickham.
But this idea that Jesus, you are above every other name.
Your name and position shadow them all.
So one of the core values of Canvas is uniting for the sake of the gospel.
And we can agree that Jesus is the most important thing.
So it is my honor and privilege to announce my brother, Sam Rogers, will be preaching for us today.
He's the pastor of Hope Valley Church.
He's no stranger, but I want to introduce you for all the people.
So Sam, I want to welcome you and thank you for ministering to all of us.
So my good friend and brother, Sam Rogers.
Welcome, everybody.
Thanks for being here.
Am I on?
If I need to do anything, we good?
I'm just going to keep talking.
There it is.
All right, now we're back.
Okay, before we get into the sermon, can I get into a completely unrelated, weird quirk of my personality?
Just so we can all get to know each other better.
Okay, here it is.
I get really excited about really mundane, like, gadgets and stuff, or even just, like, conveniences.
Does that make sense to anybody?
Okay, like, my brother and I were traveling, and my actual brother, not my brother over here, and we're traveling.
You guys ever seen it at hotels?
Some hotels have what I call a pancake printer.
Have you guys seen this?
Am I good?
Am I standing somewhere weird on the podium?
You ever seen this?
It's like a machine at, like, a hotel, like, you know, continental breakfast, and you literally say, like, I want two pancakes, and then it just starts, and two pancakes shoot out the side.
Has anyone seen this?
It, like, goes, it has, like, batter.
It has, like, a reservoir of batter, and it goes, bloop, and it goes on a conveyor belt, and then it goes between hot rollers, and a pancake sticks out.
And I'm a grown man.
I'm 40, thank you.
I'm 41, and I have totally printed more pancakes than I needed, because I just wanted to, I stood there, and I was, like, how fast do they come out?
If I put four, do they just, like, can I pick it up and aim it at people?
Like, they go, this triggers?
Okay, so, like, and I'm, like, I'm texting people, like, have you guys seen pancakes?
Okay, my brother is the same way, and so we were geeking out.
Here's what triggered that totally, like, it's not even a sermon illustration, okay, guys, this is a random story about, yeah, okay, here's what it is.
I walked up, and I had my water bottle, and I was thinking, where am I gonna put this?
And I was, like, maybe on the floor, and then I saw there was a cup holder.
There.
I've done a lot of preaching, guys.
I've never seen a cup holder on a podium before.
Maybe they're there, and I don't notice them, but I felt myself get, like, unjustifiably excited.
This is so cool.
Like, I've almost paused to take a picture and sent it to my brother, who's back in Ohio, and be like, the podium has a cup holder.
It's like a little holster.
It's like, I can just, you know what I mean?
And just keep going.
All right.
The sermon is not about pancakes or water or modern conveniences.
Sorry, that was just a complete diversion, but I think we're good now.
We good?
All right.
So, I'm gonna talk, just as we get open here, just about where we've been and where we're going, all right, as you guys have been.
I believe, in the last four weeks on the topic of community, right, the practice of community, which is great, right?
You're talking about becoming committed family, right?
Committed family, sharing life, joys, confession together.
Love that, right?
In our own house churches at Hope Valley, we've been talking for about, what's today?
Week 10 on church relationship, which we've been defining as the holy work of being the body of Christ.
Because when you do the hard work of relationship, okay?
You guys know what I'm talking about.
Okay, when you do the hard work of relationship, it's a holy work, right?
Amen.
Because when my brother and sister offend me or disappoint me or aren't there for me in the way I want them to be, and I go to them, and we talk it through and we work it through, we are knitting the body of Christ together.
Right?
We're literally taking the body of Christ on this earth and we're knitting it together and making it stronger, right?
Stronger muscles, stronger ligaments, right?
None of that can happen if the moment I'm slightly unhappy with you, I go find a difference.
Right?
In fact, what we're doing is we're telling the body of Christ apart when we do that, right?
So it's a holy work.
And that's, I think, really motivating for me personally, right?
Because sometimes it's like, oh, I'm so tired.
I don't want to go to church this morning.
Or like, you know, I'm going to go to church, but I'm going to avoid that person because they're just too much.
Guys, we know who we're talking about.
Yeah.
Emily, this is an intervention for you, Emily Child.
So we forgot the banner.
I'm sorry.
You've been causing a lot of problems here with what I've heard.
That's why Ryan called me.
No, I'm joking.
I'm completely messing.
For those of you who don't know, Emily and I work together.
We share an office at the rescue mission, so I'm picking on her a lot.
Sorry.
Right, but so it's a holy work, right?
And that's a motivation for me to do it.
And so the community practice you guys have been talking about, I'm sure has been, I haven't been here for it, but, you know, I've seen the notes.
And it looks like some good stuff.
And so today starts the next series.
I think it's four weeks.
Is that right, Corey?
Is anyone else hearing a tremendous amount of, like, weird echo off my mic?
Is that?
Okay.
Is that what it is?
Do you want me to get back this?
Oh, bring it closer.
I never have a mic on my face.
Is that?
That was it.
Excellent.
Thank you for that tip.
I remember that now going forward.
How's that?
That's even better, I think.
All right.
So this is the next four weeks is this topic of service, right?
Which I think the leadership of Canvas has rightly paired with community because if you're going to be in community, you have to get ready to serve.
Right?
You have to get ready to serve if you're going to be in community.
In fact, if you go, I want to be in community, but I would also like to not serve, that's not going to work.
Right?
One of my favorite quotes from any TV show ever is, you're not in the mood, get in the mood.
If you guys know, then you know.
Okay?
So service and community definitely go together because if you're going to be in community, then you have to get ready to serve because the people in the community with you are going to have needs.
Right?
Like, hey, can we be in close relationship and you never need anything from me ever?
That would be great.
First of all, it's not even close relationship, really, if we're talking about it.
Right?
That's the kind of relationship I can have with like a random person on a subway.
That's not real community.
Okay?
So we're going to start on the topic today.
And as we begin this topic today, I want to get you thinking of service.
This is kind of the core of today's message.
I want to get us thinking of service as really both the natural, okay?
Really both the natural and the intentional result of something.
Okay?
There are some results that are both, they partly happen naturally, okay?
And they partly happen intentionally.
Right?
So if I love somebody, there are some ways in which I will relate to them that will just kind of happen naturally because I love them and I don't have to think about it.
And then there's other ways I have to relate to them that have to be very intentional.
And only by having both the natural and the intentional outflow am I really bringing full shape to it.
Does that make sense?
Okay?
So we want to think of service as having both of those things.
It has both a natural and an intentional, it's both the natural and the intentional result of something.
Okay?
And so service is a spiritual practice.
You might say, well, is it a spiritual practice?
I mean, couldn't like, you know, anybody do it?
I mean, depends on what we're talking about by service, of course.
But service is a spiritual practice because when we serve, we are doing the actual work of aligning our behavior to the character of Christ.
Right?
It's a powerful statement.
Corey already said it this morning.
Mark chapter 10, verse 45.
This is just saying he goes, for even the Son of Man did not come to be served.
Right?
But to give his life and to serve.
And give his life for the ransom of many.
Right?
And so think about like the weight of that with the coming from Jesus.
Master and king of the universe comes to the earth not to be served as he rightly ought to be.
Okay?
And then we talk about foot washing already.
That was giving me a whole tangent over there, like on the sidelines.
Right?
Because think about when Jesus washed his disciples' feet.
He was like, if you don't let me do this, you don't have any part of me.
Part in me.
Right?
And then he's like, by the way, I dig this so that you'll remember that because his serving isn't greater than his master,
if I get down and wash your feet, you're getting even lower.
Right?
Okay.
We're hearing it.
So when we serve, it's a spiritual practice because we're doing the actual tangible work of our behavior to align our behavior to the character of Jesus.
And of course, being like Jesus is the goal of spiritual health and maturity.
It is.
Right?
Spiritual formation.
I'm going to use this term a lot today.
And I'm sure we've had some various ways of defining that.
Just for simplicity, I'm just going to talk about spiritual formation as growing in spiritual health and maturity.
Okay?
So things that are spiritually formative in my life are the things that will grow my spiritual health and grow my spiritual maturity.
And you might go, okay, well then, what does maturity look like?
And the answer, it looks exactly like Jesus.
Right?
So I don't just want to, it's multilaterally, right?
It's not just like, well, I'm following Jesus.
I should be like Jesus.
It is Jesus has demonstrated for me, if a human being were doing everything perfectly all the time, what would that look like?
We don't know what that looks like.
Right?
The closest thing we have is Corey.
No, I'm joking.
I'm joking.
Corey's like, don't put that wig on me.
Don't put that wig on me.
No, no, no.
Right?
But Jesus is that example.
So it's almost like God saying, okay, watch this.
I'm going to do it myself.
Right?
I've taught you.
I've been telling you and telling you and telling you how to live as a mature human being.
Okay, I know it's a struggle.
You know what?
I'm just going to do it myself and you watch.
This is what Jesus did.
Right?
And so Jesus is the perfect measure of maturity.
That's what Ephesians 4 is all about.
Right?
If you go read that.
Okay?
So spiritual formation is growing in spiritual health and maturity.
And Jesus is that perfect image.
We're looking for a reference point.
So how do you know, how do you measure spiritual health and maturity?
That's a great question.
Right?
How do I know that I'm healthy, that I'm maturing?
What's that process?
How do you know when you're maturing?
Right?
Because it's a process.
Okay, we can joke all day long, but the reality is our whole life here on the earth will be
a process of growing in maturity and getting closer and closer to the mark.
Right?
And so how do I know when I'm doing this?
And how do I know when I'm doing this?
Right?
How do I know when I'm regressing?
By the way, if you do not think that you can spiritually regress, let me like shout from
the rooftops and warn you today, I have watched it happen.
I've watched it happen.
And I wish I could say I've watched it happen a handful of times.
And I wish I could say it was only people that I didn't have a lot of confidence in.
Right?
If you don't think you can spiritually regress, if you can lose the knowledge of God that
you once held, if you can spiritually deform, you can.
So we should just be sober about that.
Okay?
It's not like, you know, like when people are rock climbing, they have that little thing.
I've never rock climbed.
Maybe there's rock climbers in here.
Do I look like I rock climb?
Come on, guys.
Come on.
No, it's not happening.
If you lay the wall down, I can do it.
Right?
But I've watched people do it.
And it's strenuous work.
Right?
And what I've noticed is like they kind of go up and they kind of like lock on.
They lock on.
So like if they fall, they don't fall all the way back down to the bottom.
Right?
They've got a...
Okay.
Spiritual formation is not like that.
It's like free climbing.
Okay?
You can fall.
You can fall all the way back down.
So we want to just be sober.
I'm not trying to make you paranoid.
Okay?
It's not going to happen without you really noticing unless you just decide to blind yourself.
But don't be paranoid, but be sober is what I'm saying.
Okay?
So how do you know when you're spiritually maturing?
How do you know when you're spiritually regressing?
Is it how good you are at following God's rules?
I know everyone's like, I'm not answering.
This is a trick question.
I can see it in your faces.
Okay?
We might like...
Okay.
We might know intellectually that, well, that can't be the right answer.
But I'm not talking about what you know.
I'm talking about what you act like.
Right?
Okay?
Because what I actually know is what I do.
Anyone here have teenagers?
Or have had them in the past?
God bless you.
We were all teenagers, too.
We know how they are.
By the way, I was a youth pastor for 13 years.
I absolutely love working with teenagers.
It sounds like I dislike them all the time.
Like, I just give them a hard time because I love them so much.
Right?
But they're the worst.
And we were the worst, too.
We were the worst, too.
Right?
And one of the things teenagers always do is you tell them something that they clearly
don't know because they're not doing it.
And what do they say?
Oh, I know.
I got two boys.
My two oldest are 16 and 18.
They're both at Hanley High School.
And I won't drop names right now in case anybody's watching online.
But these guys, Jonathan and Alexander.
But these guys are, right?
Really common thing, you know, is that, right?
I give them instruction.
I know, Dad.
My mom, my mom, their mom gives them instruction.
I know, Mom.
And I will walk into the room, and I'll do this.
My man!
I'll do it just like that.
If you knew, what am I talking about?
I'll say that.
You know, sometimes, you know, Dad, you just got to get a little, you know, you got to get
a little.
Amen.
You got to, you got to, it's just a wake up.
I'm not smacking them, okay?
This, I'm just clapping.
I have found this is all you need.
Just a little, just a little, right?
Hopefully, I'm not messing up the sound system with all the clapping.
What I'll do, I'll go, my man, if you knew, what are we in here talking about?
Your mom and I are bored?
We just figured, let's go rehearse everything that our children already execute perfectly
on.
Just for the sake of making them more frustrated with us than they already are by the fact that
we exist in the house and provide everything that they need all the time, 24-7, for the
last 18 years.
Yeah.
Like, what are we here for?
And I'll say to them, I'll go, if you knew, I wouldn't be talking.
If you knew, you'd be doing.
So, why am I bringing that analogy?
Because we, guys, we're just big teenagers.
That's all we are.
All right, so we can laugh at a teenager and go, oh, yeah, man, there's 17-year-olds that
way.
That's you.
You just do it better and less obviously because you've gotten smarter at how to pass the
buck.
All right, I'm just like, we're just keeping it real, okay?
I'm talking to myself, right?
Someone hold a mirror so I can just say this to myself, right?
And so, what we really know is what we really do.
Okay, so how do we know that we're maturing, right?
So, we might know, well, of course, the answer isn't, you know, that I follow up God's rules,
but is that how we behave?
I must be, you know, well, I've not been beating people and cheating on my wife and
embezzling money from my company and, you know, all those kinds of things.
So, I must be spiritually maturing.
So, we kind of, you know, because we're behaving well, we convince ourselves that we're spiritually
maturing, right?
Or is it how consistent we are in spiritual disciplines?
Guys, by the way, all these are good.
Should you follow God's laws and rules?
100%, yes.
Should you be on top of your spiritual disciplines?
Absolutely.
Can you do both of those things perfectly or nearly perfectly and not be growing spiritually
at all?
Yes.
That's what we're getting at.
Okay?
So, how do you know that you're maturing or regressing?
As with anything, if you use the wrong measure, you're going to get the incorrect results.
So, that's what we're going to get into, okay?
So, one of the things that I've talked about already is we tend to measure our performance.
Okay?
We measure our performance.
This happens because we focus on the how of spiritual formation, and we're not focusing
on the why of spiritual formation, right?
Well, this is how I spiritually, you know, grow and mature, okay?
But why?
For what?
What's the point?
You ever wonder the why?
Or are you just absorbed with the how, engraving yourself on how well your performance looks,
right?
We look at how well we're doing the things, you know?
So, for example, I'm going to church every Sunday, I'm praying, I'm reading my Bible,
I'm not being a terrible human being in my conduct and behavior, I have no criminal record,
I haven't been drunk since my 20s, whatever, right?
All right.
What's it like to be in a room with you?
Do the people that you love know that you love them?
And how do they know that?
Right?
So, we often look at the performance, we look at how well we're doing the things.
And we often make this mistake because our, we are thinking of a why, but actually our
why is selfish.
And when your why is selfish, then you begin to think of your performance, because if everything's
all about me, then all I got to do is just make sure that I cross my T's and I dot my
I's and I mind my P's and Q's, right?
And then I should get all the blessings of God flowing into my life and be happy, wealthy,
and blessed, right?
Because our why is selfish.
Spiritual formation is not about keeping you out of trouble or just making your life better.
In other words, your spiritual formation isn't just for your benefit.
I'm saying again for those in the back, your spiritual formation is not just for your benefit.
If this was all about you, if this was the you show, okay, you would just teleport to heaven the moment you got saved.
Right?
Like, honestly, you ever ask yourself, like, what are you still doing here?
Okay?
Spiritual formation isn't about keeping us out of trouble.
And it's not just about blessing our lives, making our lives better.
Well, I should pray and read the Bible because my life is better when I do that.
I mean, that's true.
But is that really the point?
Like, so it's not.
You haven't caught sarcasm yet.
You haven't picked it before I'm laying down, everybody.
No, that's not it.
That's wrong.
Okay?
We think it is, and that's why we tend to think about our performance, right?
Spiritual formation is actually about shaping us into the image of Christ
so that we can partner with him in restoring the world.
Let me say it again.
Spiritual formation is about shaping us into the image of Christ
so that we can partner with him in restoring the world.
Okay?
So, your spiritual formation is actually for the benefit of other people.
And by the way, this isn't like a new idea.
It's actually like the first three chapters of Genesis.
This guy knows where I'm going, right?
What were Adam and Eve's job?
Right?
You go, oh, gardening, animal husbandry.
Yes, yeah, yeah.
But what was their job?
Let us make male and female in our image.
That's what God said.
Why?
Why is God putting his image on the earth?
We're partners.
And managing his creation.
And in the kingdom of heaven, it's about advancing the gospel
and rescuing this world and its people from darkness and death and bondage.
Right?
How effective will I be at that?
How effective of a partner with Christ will I be in his work
if I don't look anything like him?
If my values aren't aligned with his values,
if my goals aren't aligned with his goals,
if my character's not aligned with this character.
Right?
So, God is doing a working you because he wants a working buddy.
You can think of it simply like that.
Right?
And so, that means that my spiritual formation is,
yes, I mean, okay, is it going to benefit me?
Yeah.
Like, as a bonus.
You know?
Will my life be better if I'm less of a jerk?
Yes, it will be better if I'm less of a jerk.
Should I just stop being a jerk for my own benefit?
No.
What about other people?
Right?
Okay.
All right.
So, we tend to measure the performance, right?
And that's where we're getting it wrong.
What we should be measuring is the fruit.
Okay?
Fruit's a lot harder to fake, everybody.
Fruit's a lot harder to fake.
And it might help you if you think about this
and just the way you observed it in other people's lives
because, as we all know,
we are way better at evaluating other people
than our own selves.
Okay?
That's just true.
Let's just embrace that part of our humanity together
and go, yep, we're gonna own it.
We are?
Okay.
So, sometimes it's helpful to first look at this
or where you've seen it elsewise
because it's more obvious.
How many people in this room,
just raise your hands,
you've known somebody
where all their spiritual disciplines are on point
and they don't look or act anything like Jesus in your life?
Anyone ever met those people?
Oh, I've been going to church every Sunday for 30 years.
Really?
You ever think that?
Pastors have all kinds of thoughts.
I meet people and I'm like,
oh, don't advertise that.
Please don't share your church name.
I'm not the only one, right?
How is that happening?
It happens because of what I'm talking about here.
You're measuring performance,
you're not measuring fruit.
Okay.
We're gonna go to Matthew chapter seven.
You know what's interesting about fruit?
Fruit does a lot of things.
One of the things fruit does
is fruit identifies what plant you're looking at.
Right?
Do you know if I look at like a apple tree,
like an orange tree,
I don't know, limes, whatever.
You know, I can't,
I mean, I'm sure there's differences in leaves
and barks and stuff.
I don't know all that.
I know it's an apple tree
because I go,
there's apples on it.
There's a lot of,
oh, we're in an orchard.
How do I know that?
Because there's apples everywhere.
Right?
Matthew chapter seven, verse 16.
That's what Jesus said.
He said,
you'll recognize them by their fruit.
Right?
You'll recognize them by their fruit.
Are grapes,
are grapes gathered from thorn bushes
or figs from thistles?
I love when Jesus gets like all that just straight.
Like, guys, think about this.
When you get grapes,
where are you getting them off of?
Right?
He says,
in the same way,
every good tree produces good fruit,
like a bag tree produces bag fruit.
Right?
A good tree can't produce bag fruit.
Neither can a bag tree produce good fruit.
Right?
Think about that simple analogy for a minute.
It's pretty hard to fake fruit.
Plus, fruit actually tells you
a lot of other things about the plant.
Right?
If I see a tree growing
with some nasty apples on it,
I'm not going to conclude,
I bet that tree's real healthy.
I bet it's doing,
isn't that weird
that that good healthy tree
is growing these nasty apples?
Right?
No, exactly.
So fruit is also an indicator
of the health of the plant.
Helps you identify the plant.
Helps you know how healthy that plant is
because fruit is a kind of an automatic result.
Right?
Apples don't,
apple trees aren't sitting there
working hard at making apples.
That's just what they do.
Right?
And so we can say
and we can claim
and we can act whatever we want,
but the fruit reveals the truth
of what is really happening inside of us.
You guys know
that I can preach a good sermon
and go home
and be a terrible husband?
I'm sorry
if you haven't found that out yet.
That actually happens more often
than you might know.
But it's true.
Right?
And I can show up to Bible study
and I can correctly
and accurately exposit
the text of Scripture
and pray together with you
and it's good
and go home
and abuse my children.
Now, those are extreme.
Right?
I can sing all day long
about God's grace
and patience
and mercy
in my life
and then I can go
be an unnecessary jerk
to the waiter
at lunch today.
Okay?
So the fruit
identifies
what I'm looking at.
Right?
I can say
and claim
and act
whatever I want,
but it's the fruit
of my life
that tells you
what's really happening
inside me.
Okay?
Who picks the fruit
off the plant?
This goes back
to the selfishness aspect.
Right?
Like, does an apple tree
sit there
and grab
apples
and like,
ooh, these are so big.
So the fruit
of the plant,
right?
Think of this,
the fruit growing on me,
I'm not the one
picking it
and eating it.
You are.
Right?
So fruit isn't something
I pick off my branches,
it's something
you pick off my branches.
You can't judge how,
you can judge
how healthy a plant is
in part
by the fruit
that it produces,
right?
So again,
if I'm thinking about this
like just bigger picture
and my spiritual formation
and the work
I'm actually doing
I'm letting the Holy Spirit
do inside me,
right?
This goes back
to the idea
that my spiritual formation
isn't for my benefit
and I also can't
really judge
my own fruit.
Anyone ever heard
somebody defend themselves
where you're calling out,
you might not be using language,
but you're essentially
calling out the bad fruit
and they're like,
oh no, man,
my fruit's so good.
They're like,
your apples are kind of gross.
Like, no, man,
those big old red
delicious apples
are so juicy.
They're like,
no, they aren't,
right?
So as I'm measuring
my spiritual health
and maturity,
right?
One of the ways,
one of the critical ways
that's measured
is actually by the way
other people
are experiencing me.
So this is all
important things
to think of.
What kind of fruit
then should be growing
on our branches?
It's a good question
for us to ask.
Here's one question
we can ask
to aim at that question,
right?
What kind of fruit
should be growing
on our branches?
Am I becoming
more like Jesus
in my character
and in my action?
Right?
Not just in my
following rules.
Am I doing
the Christian thing?
the things?
Right?
This is one of the reasons,
can I just go off script
for a minute
and circle back
to the,
okay,
I'm trying to be good guys.
I'm sorry.
But if we go back
to the community thing,
right?
This is one of the,
this,
okay,
community,
hard work relationship.
You know,
one of the reasons
why we don't deal
with conflict
and hard relationship
issues in the church
is because we're
too busy producing
fake fruit.
Okay,
here's what I mean
by fake fruit,
right?
I'm gonna go to church
and be a nice Christian
and be super nice
to everyone all the time
and when you ask me
how I'm doing,
I'm gonna tell you
I'm too blessed
to be stressed,
right?
And when there's
an actual issue
in a relationship,
I'm not gonna talk
about it with you
because after all,
that's not what
real Christians do,
right?
We just be super nice
and forgiving all the time
and never call out
anything ever at all
until eventually,
of course,
I can't take it anymore
and then I silently,
quietly leave this church
and go to another church
and continue to talk
to the circuit.
All because I've been working
on fake fruit.
I think,
right?
I read the fruit
of the spirit
and we're gonna get there.
I read the fruit
of the spirit
and I think,
oh,
okay,
I have to really work
at being patient
and merciful
and kind
and self-controlled
and, you know,
not actually being those things.
I'm just gonna fake
them really good.
When we forget,
apple trees
aren't working
at being apple trees.
Right?
Apples grow
on apple trees
because that's
what the apple tree is.
So if I'm looking
at the fruit
and trying to work backwards
so I can manufacture it,
then none of it's real.
All right,
that's my little diversion.
So am I becoming
more like Jesus
in my character
and my action?
You know,
Jesus called out
elephants and runes.
Jesus actively worked
to destroy
and tear down
fake peace
in order to build
real peace.
Right?
1 John 2,
verse 6 says,
the one who says
he remains in him,
remains in Jesus,
should walk
just as he walked.
So this is one
of the fruits
in my life
that I'm looking at.
And by the way,
I don't just wanna
self-evaluate that.
I'm listening
for feedback.
I'm humbling myself.
Right?
For other people,
is being around Sam
starting to feel
a little bit more
like being around Jesus
or not?
Right?
Man,
I've known Sam
for 10 years.
He's become
so much more patient,
so much more self-controlled,
so much more faithful,
so much more service-oriented.
Right?
You're seeing,
and we know these people too,
right?
We talked about
some bad examples,
but we know these people too.
We're like,
man,
that's spiritual fruit.
Right?
It's fruit.
Okay.
Another one,
is my personal spiritual formation
blessing the people around me?
Not just am I improving
as a person
in my character,
in my behavior,
in my actions,
right?
But are the people around me
being blessed
by my spiritual formation?
So if we go back,
is my time
in studying the word
in prayer,
for example,
is that making
my wife's experience
of her husband
more positive?
Is that making
my children's experience
of their father
more positive,
right?
Are they being blessed
by the work
that I'm doing internally?
Right?
And then are the people
around me?
Is my spiritual formation
manifesting
in service
to other people?
back onto our topic today.
It's a really important
question for us to ask.
Is my spiritual formation
manifesting
in the lives
of other people
in service
to them?
So,
how do we produce fruit?
As I've said
at the beginning,
fruit
is both automatic
and intentional.
right?
And here's what I mean
about automatic,
right?
If I,
if I'm really
receiving
the love of God
in my life,
right?
Like just,
when I get alone,
okay?
When I get alone
and there's nobody watching,
if I really
am beginning
to soak in
and receive
and be internally
transformed
by the love
of God
and the truth
in my life,
there will be
things in my behavior
that aren't honestly,
automatically
just are happening.
That's true.
Okay?
Right?
Just like,
by the way,
you leave a plant alone
and it's gonna make the fruit,
but you can cultivate it
and make the plant
more fruitful,
right?
Right?
This is why
we don't just like
throw seeds out
and like leave them alone
and come back in a year,
right?
This is why there's farms
and everything else.
So the plant's gonna grow it,
but how good
will the fruit be?
Right?
So there's an automatic part
and there's an intentional part,
right?
As we more fully receive
the love of God,
His love pours out of us.
Okay?
How you treat others then
is a direct indicator
of your own receptiveness
to God's love for you.
I have to think
we need to think about that today.
Okay?
Because here's what
I don't want you guys to hear.
I want you to go home
and be like,
oh man,
now like this burden of work.
You guys with me?
Like man,
now I gotta keep up
appearances even more,
right?
Now I gotta work even harder.
Okay, guys,
you know like the more
that I've actually
just gotten good
at loving my wife,
the less work our marriage is?
Right?
The more that I
let myself slow down
and think about
how much I love my children,
the less hard it is
to be a halfway decent dad,
right?
It's not like
go work a whole bunch more.
It's completely reorient
yourself here for a minute.
Okay?
How I'm treating
other people
is a direct indicator
of my own receptiveness
to God's love
in my life.
So there's an aspect of that
that's gonna be automatic,
right?
Because the aim,
which is the first,
let me just say this.
every single person
I've personally encountered
in seasons of my life
where I've been
the same person,
but every person
I've encountered
that is unforgiving,
that is selfish,
as I've gotten to know them
I've realized
how much
they have no idea
how much God loves them.
It's not most,
it is 100%.
and there's a direct
causation there
that I want to just realize
today,
right?
Because the fruit
of the Spirit,
this is Galatians 5,
22 and 23,
the fruit
of the Spirit
is love
and joy
and peace
and patience,
kindness,
goodness,
faithfulness,
gentleness,
self-control.
Paul's saying
this is what flows
out of you
when you're in the Spirit.
This is what flows
out of you
when you're letting
God's love
into your heart,
right?
And this is a,
there's a practicality
of this
because part of it
is you sit here
and sit in the morning
and you open
your Bible
when you're alone
and you're in your
small groups
during the week
and you're hearing
these wonderful truths
about God's love
for you
and you're saying,
I just don't know
if I can really believe that.
So you're closing
yourself off,
you're walling
you're not allowing
God's love
to really permeate
you as a person,
right?
And then you're
over here going,
I'm gonna like
stiff arm God's love
over here
because I was hurt
too bad,
I was abused
too bad
or I'm too hung up
on my own self-image
to believe
that I'm lovable
and then I'm gonna
go over here
and I'm gonna try
and be really loving
and gracious
and kind
and patient
with people
and I'm exhausted
and I would go,
yeah,
that's exhausting.
That's impossible.
It's unsustainable.
But instead,
if you
go to God,
how does he say
as a child?
As a child,
not as a hurt,
traumatized adult
with bad parents.
As a child.
You're in a place
where you can just
believe and receive
his love.
And now,
his love is flowing
out of you.
You're not working
at it.
Because it's,
you get what I'm
saying, right?
And so service
becomes this
automatic natural
product.
One of the things
that's beautiful
about children
is,
and I'm,
I'm younger,
so I'm eight now,
but I remember
even,
you know,
there was like
a 10-year period
where we were in
diapers nonstop.
We had five kids.
And one of the things
that really struck me
about children,
especially when they're
very small,
and you guys
have probably seen
this too,
have you ever seen
like a two or three-year-old
like kind of question
if you really love them?
I've never seen it
happen.
Ever.
Never,
any,
never did any of my
small children go,
I don't know,
Dad.
I'm just kind of
really wrestling
with like
the believability
of that statement.
You know,
I mean,
I'm not sure
that I really
deserve to be
loved by you.
They don't have
that problem.
You know,
you pick up
your little one,
you say I love you,
and they're like,
okay.
They just believe you.
And so then
these little children
come and run to Jesus,
and they're like,
stay away from Jesus,
and Jesus goes,
no, no, no.
First of all,
he's super mad
when they do that.
And he's like,
let them come to me
because the kingdom
of heaven
belongs to people
like these people.
Right?
And so you've got
to come to him
as a child
and just go,
hey, I love you.
And you go,
okay.
And you soak it in.
Right?
And as you soak it in,
it begins to transform you.
And so there's
a tremendous amount
of service
and these kind of works
and these kind of actions,
right?
They will flow out of you.
They just will.
Right?
And if they're really
struggling to flow,
I would say go back
to the source
and let's start
working on that part.
Right?
Because the aim
and the destination
of the spiritual journey
is to become love.
Guys, like,
when it's,
guys, let's just fast forward
to the end, okay?
When all this is done.
Right?
What is Paul saying
in 1 Corinthians 13?
When it's all done,
what's left?
Love.
When all the work is done,
right?
When all the restoration
of the world is done,
how will we spend our time
in eternity?
Love and relationship
with one another
and the Father.
Right?
So let's just, like,
aim there now.
Because the aim
and destination
of the spiritual journey
is really to become love.
That my inner journey
of formation
would pour out of me
actively in service
to others.
Right?
And I love this verse
in 1 John chapter 4,
verse 7.
It says,
dear friends,
let us love one another
because love is from God
and everyone who loves
has been born of God
and knows Him.
And also in 1 John
chapter 3, verse 18,
it says,
let us not love in word
or in speech,
but in truth
and in action.
If you really want
to dig into this,
this is a pro tip,
okay?
Pro Bible study tip.
Just go get all up
in 1 John.
Like, just roll around in it.
You know,
listen to it,
put it in your earbuds
while you go on a jog
or if you're like me,
just sit and drink coffee
in the morning
and watch other people jog.
Because jogging,
not relaxing,
watching other people
treat their bodies healthy,
kind of relaxing.
I wasn't built for jogging,
I was built for cuddles.
That's what I always
tell my wife.
But I love that verse, right?
Because so many times,
let's just be honest,
we're loving in word
and in speech
and we're not loving
in truth and in action.
And John,
you know,
describes the Last Supper
and John is like
essentially snuggling
with Jesus
at the Last Supper.
Right?
Throughout his entire gospel,
John only refers to himself
as the disciple
that Jesus loved.
I don't think that's because
John had like an inflating ego.
It's just because
John knew who he was.
Right?
John
definitely is an apostle
that like latched onto this
and understood it.
And then you go and read like,
I mean,
he's probably like
70,
90 years old,
somewhere in that range
when he wrote 1 John.
Right?
He's like a lot of time
to think about this.
And you go read that
and he's like,
let me talk to you
about the love of God
and what it really does
in your life.
Right?
So it says in verse 18,
chapter 3,
let's not love
just in word or in speech,
but in truth
and in action.
Right?
And so,
what do we do?
Right?
How do I produce this love?
Like I said,
how do I produce this fruit?
Okay,
so part of it's gonna be automatic,
the other part's gonna be intentional.
Here's the intentional part.
Okay?
Start where you are.
If you're hearing this
and you're going,
I need to go volunteer
for an organization.
I mean,
okay,
sure.
You know,
our rescue mission
volunteer coordinator
is right here
in the front row
and she's not
a completely unlikable person
so you should come talk to her
after church service,
right?
Yeah,
that's cool.
That's cool.
Right?
But again,
you can go and,
and I've seen this,
you can go and volunteer
and feed the homeless
and the poor
at the rescue mission
and still be a jerk.
Still go out to a dinner
and be rude to the waiter
and still go to Walmart
and be rude to the cashier
if there is one there.
You know what I'm talking about?
Okay?
Start where you are.
The mundane,
ordinary,
familiar interactions
with others.
Okay?
Start where you are.
You really want to go,
all right, man,
I want to dig into
the Spirit of God,
receive His love
so that some of us
just starts,
it just starts pouring out of me.
I'm not even trying.
It's just happening.
But now I really want
to hone it,
right?
I want to go from
like a wild apple tree
to like a really well-tended
apple tree
that's like an orchard
and it's like really good fruit,
right?
Okay.
How am I going to do that?
And a lot of times
we think,
well,
I got to go do
some big thing,
right?
Well,
I'm going to put
some big project together
and we're going to have
this huge impact
for one day
so I can tell myself
that I've started
to serve people.
That's not going to
change anything, guys.
That's not how
you hone it.
Okay?
If you cannot love
your family,
your neighbors,
your friends,
then every other
show of love
is just that.
It's a show.
Okay?
You know what's
like really easy?
I could forgive
every person
in this room
significantly easier
than my own brother.
Right?
It is a lot easier
to be nice to you guys
than to my teenage times
when they're annoying me.
Right?
It's a lot easier
to come and go
and volunteer somewhere
and do a thing
and then go home
and I have no idea
who my next door neighbor is,
what their needs are,
what they're struggling with.
You guys see what I'm saying?
Okay?
The real hard work
is in the mundane,
not flashy,
no one's going to
take a picture of this
and share it on Facebook
to show how charitable
you are, right?
The mundane,
normal,
everyday interactions.
When I'm getting to know
other people in ministry
and I want to get
like a sense of like,
do I trust this person
well enough
to actually get involved
with them in ministry?
I try to make sure
that we go and do
really mundane things together
where people would be
very comfortable
being rude.
I do.
I'm on purpose.
You know?
You know the most things
like let's go out
to coffee and dinner.
I'm like,
I have a secret agenda
the entire time.
I know everyone
goes out to coffee
and dinner.
I'm going to watch
the waitress.
I'm serious.
Right?
Because the real levity
into the Holy Spirit
working in my life
is that it just
is happening.
It's not put on.
Okay?
So if you can't love
your family,
neighbors,
right?
Okay?
Let's start there.
You don't need to go
join an organization
or program to do this.
This might sound
counterintuitive
coming from the guy
who's the development
director for the
Wing Chester Rescue Mission
with our volunteer
coordinator in the front row.
If you're already
doing well in these areas,
please come volunteer.
We need you.
We do.
Yeah.
Okay?
So I'm not saying...
Okay, both and.
Can we say both and?
Can we take a...
Okay, okay.
But you don't need
to go join
an organization
or program
to do this.
Okay?
You can't go,
oh, I'll go...
Oh, I'll be more
service-oriented.
I just gotta go
find someone
to volunteer.
My man.
Do you live alone?
Is there no one
in your house?
Do you have no siblings?
Do you have no friends?
What are their needs?
Do you have no church family?
How's the church doing?
Is it struggling?
Are the resources down?
Do you know?
Right?
You're enjoying
the fruits of the ministry.
Are you participating
in the planting
to make those fruits
a reality?
Right?
There's all kinds
of like just mundane things.
Right?
I know mundane
is not a sexy word,
but it's pretty
accurate though,
right?
It's like just
the ordinary stuff.
You know?
So,
when you can do this
with people,
I'll close on this.
When you can do this
with people,
yeah, we're gonna go ahead
and wrap up,
but when you do this
with people,
okay,
where there's not gonna
be a benefit back,
that's one of the ways
that you know as well.
I'll close on that.
You know,
Jesus said,
if you only love
people that love you,
right,
what credit's that to you?
He's like,
you know,
even terrible people
do that.
Right?
That's what he said.
But love people
and serve people
that can't repay you.
And then you'll actually
be acting like me.
That's what he said.
Right?
Let's have that heart
and that attitude today.
I'm gonna close this up
and we're gonna receive
communion together.
I think I'll hang for that.
Is that good?
Oh, no, no, no, no, no.
No, we're gonna trade off.
We're gonna trade off.
So let me go ahead
and close and pray
and pray.
I'm gonna have Corey come up
and he's gonna lead us
in communion this morning.
So, Lord,
we just thank you
for your word
to us today.
God, I pray
that you would teach us.
Lord, that you would teach us
what these things mean.
Lord, help us
to open our hearts
to you
so that as your love
and your power flow
is into us, God,
that that would flow out
in service to the people
around us,
that our service
wouldn't be put on,
our service wouldn't be
performative,
but our service
would be the honest,
natural,
good fruit
of a life
and a heart
that is filled
by you.
Lord,
our desire
is to be like you
in every way.
We need you,
Lord.
Soften our hearts.
Meet us
where we're at.
Take us
to that next step
of growth
and maturity.
Lord,
we thank you
for these things.
We thank you
for your word.
And Lord,
most of all,
we thank you
for your love
which sustains us,
which birthed us,
Lord God,
and which carries us
every day.
We thank you
for all these things,
Lord,
in your name.
Amen.